Guide to the Socialist Party (U.S.) Correspondence TAM.056.009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- SERIES IV: NEW YORK CITY CORRESPONDENCE, 1908-1946; 131306
  Series IV: The New York City Correspondence (frames IX:53 98), which follow the New York State files in the filming order, constitute the largest group of records in this collection. Most of these files pertain to events of the 1930s, but there are important items for the 1910s, 1920s, and 1940s as well. of major importance in these files are papers relating to the Socialist Party split and the fur workers dispute. Regarding the party split, there are items pertaining to communist infiltration of the Socialist Party, the suspense of the New York State branch, the militancy of the Young People's Socialist League, and the 1934 Declaration of Principles. The furriers' union papers (IX:69 IX:73) include correspondence from Norman Thomas, minutes of Socialist Party meetings on the "communist" International Fur Workers Union, and the investigative report written by Norman Thomas on the fur workers dispute.
  Another interesting aspect of these files are the papers relating to the Women's Committee of the New York City local (IX:74, IX:76, IX:81, IX:88, IX:91). Beginning in 1935, the Women's Committee sponsored a series of meetings known as the "Women's Conference Against the High Cost of Living." These meetings featured speeches by prominent socialists and discussion sessions on such topics as the standard of living, unemployment insurance, social security, socialized medicine, municipal waste, sales taxes, and the Child Labor Amendment. The Women's Committee papers include speeches, outlines, correspondence, and reports regarding these consumer oriented meetings.
  Other papers contained in the New York City files relate to such issues and events as the Socialist Party's relationship with organized labor, the 1937 Appeal Clarity group conflict, the differences between communists and socialists concerning the "Popular Front" question, and Socialist Party electoral activities. In the pre 1930 files, there are papers pertaining to the Bronx Agitation Committee, Kings County local, and the East Side Agitation Committee. The major correspondents in these files are Julius Gerber (IX:78, IX:84) and August Claessens (IX:77, IX:83), but there are also numerous letters from William Mailly, W. J. Ghent, Charles Edward Russell, Adolph Germer, Norman Thomas, Alfred Baker Lewis, Jack Altman, Clarence Senior, Esther Friedman, Darlington Hoopes, Mark Starr, Paul Porter, Louis Waldman, Charles Solomon, Daniel W. Hoan, James Oneal, Theodore Schapiro, Dorothy Kenyon, Bertha H. Mailly, and Gerhart Seger.
  - New York City, Kings County, Sep 1908-Jul 1909, undated; 131360 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:53
  - New York City, Feb 1911-Dec 1911, undated; 131359 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:54
  - New York City, Jan 1912-Nov 1912, undated; 131358 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:55
  - New York City, Bronx Agitation Committee, Jul 1912-Dec 1912; 131357 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:56
  - New York City, Feb 1913-Sep 1913; 131356 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:57
  - New York City, Nov 1915-Dec 1915; 131355 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:58
  - New York City, Jun 1916-Oct 1916; 131354 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:59
  - New York City, Minutes, 1916, undated; 131353 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:60
  - New York City, Mar 1917, undated; 131352 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:61
  - New York City, East Side Agitation Committee, Feb 1917-Oct 1917, undated; 131351 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:62
  - New York City, Nov 1920, Jan 1921-Jun 1921; 131350 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:63
  - New York City, Mar 1923-Apr 1923; 131349 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:64
  - New York City, Apr 1923-Aug 1930; 131348 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:65
  - New York City, Mar 1931-Dec 1931, undated; 131347 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:66
  - New York City, Jan 1932-Dec 1932, undated; 131346 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:67
  - New York City, Jan 1933-Dec 1933, undated; 131345 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:68
  - New York City, Furriers' Union Correspondence, Jun 1933-Jul 1933; 131344 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:69
  - New York City, Furriers' Union, Norman Thomas Correspondence, Jun 1933-Jul 1933; 131343 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:70
  - New York City, Furriers' Union, Norman Thomas Memorandum, Jun 1933; 131342 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:71
  - New York City Furriers' Union, Minutes, Jun 1933; 131341 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:72
  - New York City, Furriers' Union, Reports, Jun 1933; 131340 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:73
  - New York City, Women's Committee, Dec 1933; 131339 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:74
  - New York City, Jan 1934-Dec 1934, undated; 131338 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:75
  - New York City, Women's Committee, May 1934-Dec 1934, undated; 131337 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:76
  - New York City, August Claessens Correspondence, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131336 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:77
  - New York City, August Claessens Correspondence, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131335 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New York City, August Claessens Correspondence, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131334 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - New York City, Julius Gerber Correspondence, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131333 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:78
  - New York City, Grievance Committee, 1935, undated; 131332 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:79
  - New York City, Miscellaneous, Feb 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131331 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:80
  - New York City, Women's Committee, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131330 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:81
  - New York City, Women's Committee, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131329 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - New York City, Women's Committee, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131328 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - New York City, Women's Committee, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated; 131327 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - New York City, YPSL Crisis, Mar 1935-Jun 1935, undated; 131326 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:82
  - New York City, August Claessens Correspondence, Jan 1936-Dec 1936, undated; 131325 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:83
  - New York City, August Claessens Correspondence, Jan 1936-Dec 1936, undated; 131324 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - New York City, Julius Gerber Correspondence, Jan 1936-Dec 1936, undated; 131323 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:84
  - New York City, Membership Lists, 1918; 131322 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:85
  - New York City, Membership Lists, 1918; 131321 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - New York City, Miscellaneous, Mar 1936-Jul 1936, undated; 131320 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:86
  - New York City, Organization and Propaganda, Aug 1936-Nov 1936; 131319 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:87
  - New York City, Women's Committee, Jan 1936-Jun 1936, undated; 131318 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:88
  - New York City, Women's Committee, Jan 1936-Jun 1936, undated; 131317 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - New York City, Financial Papers, Jan 1937-Jun 1937, undated; 131316 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:89
  - New York City, Mimeographed Reports, Apr 1937-Aug 1937, undated; 131315 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:90
  - New York City, Women's Committee, Mar 1937; 131314 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:91
  - New York City, Mar 1939-Aug 1939, undated; 131313 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:92
  - New York City, Dec 8, 1940, undated; 131312 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:93
  - New York City, Apr 1941; 131311 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:94
  - New York City, Jun 1944; 131310 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:95
  - New York City, Jan 1945-May 1945; 131309 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:96
  - New York City, Apr 1946; 131308 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:97
  - New York City, undated; 131307 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 14, Frame IX:98
- SERIES V: FRAGILE ORIGINALS, 300944
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 1, FOLDER 1 through BOX 1, FOLDER 9, 300945 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 1, FOLDER 10 through BOX 1, FOLDER 17, 300946 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 1, FOLDER 18 through BOX 1, FOLDER 21, 300947 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 1, FOLDER 23, 300948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 1, FOLDER 24 through BOX 1, FOLDER 27, 300949 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 2, FOLDER 1 through BOX 2, FOLDER 6, 300950 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 2, FOLDER 7 through BOX 2, FOLDER 15, 300951 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 2, FOLDER 21 through BOX 2, FOLDER 23, 300952 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 2, FOLDER 24 through BOX 2, FOLDER 26, 300953 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 3, FOLDER 1 through BOX 3, FOLDER 2, 300954 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 3, FOLDER 3 through BOX 3, FOLDER 8, 300955 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 3, FOLDER 9 through BOX 3, FOLDER 13, 300956 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 3, FOLDER 14 through BOX 3, FOLDER 15, 300957 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 3, FOLDER 16 through BOX 3, FOLDER 21, 301195 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 4, FOLDER 1 through BOX 4, FOLDER 2, 302043 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 4, FOLDER 4, 302044 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 4, FOLDER 5, 302045 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 4, FOLDER 6, 302046 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 4, FOLDER 7 through BOX 4, FOLDER 9, 302312 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 5, FOLDER 1 through BOX 5, FOLDER 2, 302313 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 5, FOLDER 3 through BOX 5, FOLDER 5, 302821 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 5, FOLDER 6, 302822 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 5, FOLDER 7, 302823 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 6, FOLDER 1 through BOX 6, FOLDER 2, 303895 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 6, FOLDER 3 through BOX 6, FOLDER 5, 303896 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 6, FOLDER 6 through BOX 7, FOLDER 1, 308335 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 7, FOLDER 2 through BOX 7, FOLDER 11, 308336 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - FRAGILE ORIGINALS from BOX 7, FOLDER 12 through BOX 7, FOLDER 16, 308337 (Box 11, Folder 3)